<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Neurosience]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib\media\favicon.png</url><title>Neurosience</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 19:01:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib\rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 19:01:14 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Action Potential]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The action potential is a scientific description that explains a neural phenomenon. The impetus to describe this phenomenon can be traced to several origins in thought. The Greek physician, Galen, provided one of the first dominating theories of the nervous system, describing the motion of fluids secreted from brain tissue and conveyed by nerves. <br>It is important to note that most descriptions of the action potential are meant to describe general motifs. The most basic definition of an action potential describes the properties which produce the active propagation of a signal through a cell: a brief 1-10 ms large amplitude depolarization which is propagated in an all-or-none fashion. An action potential (AP) is "all-or-none" as compared to passive, graded signaling; an AP is like a flipping a light switch on and off, while graded signaling (like neurotransmitter release) are like adjusting a light dimmer. <br>Like a switch that goes on and off, an AP represents a fundamental unit of information in the nervous system. However, the light-switch analogy only demonstrates the idea that an AP contains a discrete unit of information. In reality, the AP is a complex, though ordered, biochemical and electrophysiological process. First, let's discuss what is taught in introductory courses to establish our framework.<br>A neuron spikes when the membrane potential is depolarized past a threshold where a cascade of voltage-gated ion channels open leading to a rapid change in membrane potential that propogates down the length of an axon. The phospholipid bilayer maintains a certain difference in electrical potential on either side; while resting, this potential is typically modeled to be -65 mVA but this can range from -40 to -80 mV where muscle cell is may be around -90 mV. Another important feature of the membrane is its selective permeability to certain molecular species, particularly Na+ and K+ ions. Sodium-potassium pumps maintain this distribution by actively pumping sodium ions out of the cell and pumping potassium ions into the cell. While at rest, potassium ions leak out of the cell through ion channels, proteins mebedded in the cell membrane that form pores, as K+ follows the concentration gradient. This state of affairs leaves the inside of the cell more negatively charged. It is the inward current of positively charged ions (Na+ and Ca2+) that perturb the resting state. The excitability of the neuron can be understood by the ability of the membrane potential to be quickly and significantly altered. As positive charge rushes in, the negative charge inside the cell is neutralized, further increasing the influx of sodium ions. This is the basis of the action potential, which is actively propagated down an axon, maintaining its amplitude until it reaches the postsynapse where it may be transduced into a chemical signal of neurotransmission.<br>
Alls signaling in the nervous system involves input, integration, conduction, and output. The input may be mechanical, chemical, or electrical. These produce graded local signals that may begin at a receptor region like a postsynapse. The information is translated into a sum of shift in membrane potential that is integrated in a region called the Axon Hillock where a high density of Na+ channels can be triggered to amplify the inputs into action potential. Information can be encoded in the frequency and and duration of spiking which can determine the amount of neurotransmitter is released<br>
The result is an explosive shift in the membrane potential of ~+40 mV.   reduced model of the action potential may describe the fast persistent Na+ current as an amplifying current while the <br>
<br>]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\action-potential.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Action Potential.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 20:20:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[DREADs]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\dreads.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/DREADs.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:31:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Electroencephalography]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\electroencephalography.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Electroencephalography.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:31:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[fMRI]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Magnetic resonance imaging is a technology built upon knowledge of an intrinsic property of protons in hydrogen nuclei known as spin. Proton spin in hydrogen atoms behave like a bar magnet, and when exposed to the strong magnetic field of an MRI machine they align. MRI machines use electromagnets constructed from superconductive material, such as niobium-titanium, cooled with liquid helium in a vacuum chamber; this cools the material to absolute zero, reducing resistance to near zero. This allows for the production of the strong magnetic fields<br>Radiofrequency (RF) pulses can be used to knock the aligned dipoles perpendicular, after which the protons return to their alignment with the magnetic field (like really stiff bobbleheads). The return to position after the RF induces a measurable current, or echo, that is received by coils in the MRI. Coils closer to the body produce better images, stronger MRI magnets result in stronger echos. <br>An MRI sequence is composed of RF pulses and echos (in sequence). The time between is measured as the time to echo (TE). Because echos weaken over time, larger pulses are needed to 'reset' the strength of the echos; the time between larger RF pulses is known as the repetition time (TR). Variations in these timings allow for imaging of different tissues and fluids. <br>
<br>T1 relaxation, or longitudinal relaxation, is how long it takes for 63% of the longitudinal magnetization to recover in the z-axis 
<br>T2 relaxation, or transverse relaxation, is how long it takes 63% of the transverse magnetization to be lost in the x and y axes<br>
T1 weighted images are best for viewing grey matter (like cortex) and T2 weighted images are better for viewing water-based fluids like cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)
<br>MRI coils that produces these frequencies are independent subunits of channels and process specific components of the MRI image. The components include amplifiers, filters, image processors, etc. The number of channels influences how much processes power in required during acquisition and also the resulting image quality. An analogy would be if you used several camera with various sensors to capture specific image properties, then stitched them together to make an ultra-quality image.<br><br><img alt="fMRI spatial information.png" src="\digital-garden\published\attachments\fmri-spatial-information.png"><br>
Larmor Equation: Magnetic field strength is proportional to the rotational frequency of hydrogen nuclei&nbsp;<br>
<br>ω = γ * B, where ω is the rotational frequency, γ is the gyromagnetic ration, and B is the magnetic field strength
<br>Varying the magnetic field along a gradient results in hydrogen nuclei having different rotational frequencies&nbsp;
<br>RF pulses can target a specific area along gradient
<br><br>Blood oxygen level dependent (BOLD) imaging is an indirect way of measuring brain&nbsp;activity in functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI). Active brain regions require increased oxygenated blood flow, and T2 weighted sequences can detect this change due to the different magnetic properties of deoxygenated Hemaglobin and oxyginated Hemaglobin.]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\fmri.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/fMRI.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 02:21:13 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="digital-garden\published\attachments\fmri-spatial-information.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="digital-garden\published\attachments\fmri-spatial-information.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fundamentum]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Action Potential" href="\digital-garden\published\action-potential.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Action Potential</a><br><a data-href="Neurons" href="\Neurons" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Neurons</a><br><a data-href="Plasticity" href="\Plasticity" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Plasticity</a><br><a data-href="Neuroscientific Methods" href="\digital-garden\published\neuroscientific-methods.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Neuroscientific Methods</a><br><a data-href="Seminal Work" href="\digital-garden\published\seminal-work.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Seminal Work</a>]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\fundamentum.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Fundamentum.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:27:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[<a data-href="Fundamentum" href="digital-garden/published/fundamentum.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fundamentum</a>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br><br>]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\laboratorium.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Laboratorium.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:06:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Forebrain]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>Neocortex
<br>Amygdala
<br>Hippocampus
<br>Basal Ganglia
<br>Lateral Ventricals
<br><br>
<br>Thalamus
<br>Hypothalamus
<br>Pituitary Gland
<br>Pineal Gland
<br>Third Ventrical
<br><br><br>
<br>Substantia nigra
<br>Red Nucleus
<br>Superior Colliculus
<br><br>
<br>Pons
<br>Cranial Nerve Nuclei
<br><a data-href="Cerebellum" href="\cerebellum.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cerebellum</a>
<br><br>
<br>Medulla Oblongata
<br>Reticular Formation
<br><br><br>The brain, or cerebrum, consists of all structures in above excluding the spinal cord. The spinal cord is included when considering the central nervous system (CNS). The brain and spinal cord develop from the formation of the neural tube, the brain arising from the anterior (rostral) and the spinal cord arising from the posterior (caudal) portion. Neural development in vertebrates is a process of continual differentiation of structures guided by genetic expression and cellular specialization.<br>The brainstem consists of the medulla, pons, and midbrain and provides regulatory functions often taken for granted by humans: blood pressure and breathing control (medulla); balance, taste, hearing, face and neck muscle control (medulla, cranial nerves); breathing, sleep, taste, movement coordination (pontine nuclei). These functions, among others, are considered autonomic and often engage rapid sensory-motor integration for things like automatic eye movements. <a data-href="for example" href="\for example" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">for example</a><br>
The reticular formation is another important structure of the brainstem, encompassing several nuclei that promote alert states and wakefulness (often called arousal). <br>What is a nucleus?
Describing what a nucleus is in neural terms
]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\neuroanatomy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Neuroanatomy.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 20:35:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Neuroscientific Methods]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-href="Patch Clamp" href="\digital-garden\published\patch-clamp.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Patch Clamp</a><br><a data-href="Local Field Potentials" href="\local-field-potentials.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Local Field Potentials</a><br><a data-href="Electroencephalography" href="\digital-garden\published\electroencephalography.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Electroencephalography</a><br><br><a data-href="Optogenetics" href="\digital-garden\published\optogenetics.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Optogenetics</a><br><a data-href="DREADs" href="\digital-garden\published\dreads.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">DREADs</a><br><br><a data-href="fMRI" href="\digital-garden\published\fmri.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">fMRI</a><br><a data-href="fNiR" href="\fNiR" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">fNiR</a>]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\neuroscientific-methods.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Neuroscientific Methods.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 01:19:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Optogenetics]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\optogenetics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Optogenetics.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:31:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Patch Clamp]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\patch-clamp.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Patch Clamp.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:31:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Proprioception]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\proprioception.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Proprioception.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:00:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Seeing]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\seeing.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Seeing.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:00:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Seminal Work]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Italian scientist Camillo Golgi and the Spaniard Santiago Ramon y Cajal, considered the forefathers of modern neuroscience, conveyed the mysterious microcosm of nervous tissues to the scrutiny of the human eye. Golgi's silver salt staining, originally called the black reaction, traces a neuron's morphology with impressive fidelity; complex dendritic branches appear as molecular etchings, fractal patterns burnt into a sea of amber. Interestingly, the nature and underlying mechanism of this process is still not well understood. 1<br><img alt="Hippocampus sketch by Camillo Golgi.bmp" src="\lib\media\hippocampus-sketch-by-camillo-golgi.bmp"><br> The Golgi Stain
Brownish-red silver chromate molecules form inside of cells within preserved tissues after exposure to potassium nitrate and silver dichromate. Unlike other staining techniques, this reaction does not require a cell-specific antibody; Golgi stains are not cell specific, yet result in a sparse (~1% of neurons) reaction. As neurons are densely packed, the Golgi stain becomes advantageous for studying various cell morphologies. 
<br>Ramon y Cajal was able to use Golgi's technique to provide evidence of what has become known as The Neuron Doctrine wherein neurons are understood as discrete cells, and the nervous system as made up from the interconnection of these cells. The movement of information in nervous tissue is done between neurons. The action potential describes the movement of electrical potential through a neuron that results in the release of neurotransmitters at the synapse. ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\seminal-work.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Seminal Work.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:28:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\hippocampus-sketch-by-camillo-golgi.bmp" length="0" type="image/bmp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\hippocampus-sketch-by-camillo-golgi.bmp"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sensation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Hearing" href="\hearing.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hearing</a><br><a data-href="Seeing" href="\digital-garden\published\seeing.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Seeing</a><br><a data-href="Tasting" href="\digital-garden\published\tasting.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Tasting</a><br><a data-href="Proprioception" href="\digital-garden\published\proprioception.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Proprioception</a>]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\sensation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Sensation.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:00:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tasting]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\tasting.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/Tasting.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 02:00:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Study of Instinct]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>digital-garden\published\the-study-of-instinct.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Published/The Study of Instinct.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 18:49:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Diffusion]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>Ions move according to Thermodynamic laws. Their movement is random, or Brownian, as they move through a medium. Diffusion is fast at short lengths and slow at long length scales.
<br>-To diffuse across a cell body (10 micrometers) takes an ion 50ms
<br>To diffuse down a dendrite (1mm) it takes an ion 10 minutes
<br>To diffuse down the length of a motor neuron (10 meters) it takes 10 Years!
<br><br>Diffusion produces a net flow of particles from regions of high concentration to regions of lower concentration<br>
The flux of particle is proportional to the concentration gradient.<br><br>Neurons can perform analog numerical integration over time<br>]]></description><link>digital-garden\diffusion.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Diffusion.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 02:43:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Jake's Virtual Laboratorium]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="The Alchemist's Laboratory.jpg" src="\digital-garden\attachments\the-alchemist's-laboratory.jpg"><br>
"Alchemist's laboratory," more specifically Heinrich Kunrath's, painted by Hans Vredeman de Vries, 16th century<br><br>I would like to open up my laboratory for public consumption to solidify my thinking into a tangible order. In the painting above, representing the alchemical work of Heinrich Khunrath's stage of eternal wisdom, all vanishes into a centralized perspectival point. Consider this as you explore this digital representation of my own alchemical exploration; I present my laboratorium, mounted upon my developing pillars of experience and reason. <br>In order to become a neuroscience PhD candidate, I must pass both a qualifying and comprehensive examination. These tests are meant to measure a student's mastery of fundamental principles in the field. Therefore, I have devised the current project as a creative study framework that takes advantage of the writing process. To maximize the potential of this work to advance my own understanding, I will be taking it upon myself to create an additional challenge: Not only will I write about neuroscientific concepts with great rigor (for I will be examined), but I intend to format it for the general public. In doing, I hope to represent my passion for what I am learning, my creativity, and my drive to understand more about the world.<br>The groundwork for the factual components of my work will come from Kandel's Principles of Neural Science, Sixth Edition, along with notes from lectures in Cellular Molecular Neuroscience, Comparative Neuroanatomy, and Systems Neuroscience. Check footnotes for citations and other resources. <br><br>Through my work I seek facere de necessitate virtutem - to make a virtue of a necessity.<br>In the Alchemist's laboratory, dormiens vigila is engraved above the entrance. Awake in sleep, how Prospero in Shakespeare's The Tempest describes his play within a play in a monolgue addressing a character and an audience, "We are such stuff as dreams are made on," that, once a performance, or some illusion, fades to thin air. In the Amphitheatrum sapientiae aeternae we are material only in the foreground, encircled by eternity, our work concentrating toward a singular point, a time within eternity--for in the seed lies the fruit. As Khunrath is seen praying in his oratorium, an oven positioned to the right of the centered table admonishes to Festine lente, hasten slowly. Take your time to cook. On the center table are strewn instruments, symbolic gifts of song and harmony that accompany the work of life. ]]></description><link>digital-garden\jake's-virtual-laboratorium.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Jake's Virtual Laboratorium.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 21:51:41 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="digital-garden\attachments\the-alchemist's-laboratory.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="digital-garden\attachments\the-alchemist's-laboratory.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Planning Research]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>Relevant, narrow, and clear
<br>Transparent, systematic assessment of prior studies and literature
<br>From the clinical research field: "PICOT" (population, intervention, comparator, outcome, and time frame)
<br>Exploratory or confirmatory?
<br><br>
<br>Helps to resuce publication bias and prevent hindsight biases
<br>Safegaurds honest research and minimizes research waste
<br>Create detailed plans for the study protocol
<br><br>
<br>Standardized operating procedures (SOP) and electronic lab notebooks enable standardized research execution. 
<br>Standardized data collection 
<br>Consistent methodology across experimental groups
<br><br>
<br>Plan the whole life-cycle of the collected data for long-term storage and later reuse. 
<br>The FAIR data principles (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable)
<br>Appropriate metadata for discovery and processing of data
<br><br><br>
<br>Questionable Research Practices:

<br>low statistical power
<br>pseudoreplication
<br>repeated inspection of data
<br>p-hacking
<br>selective reporting
<br>hypothesizing after the results are known (HARKing)
<br>Publication bias


<br>Statistical power is a precondition of reproducibility
<br><br>
<br>Similar to Linus's Law for spotting bugs in software, the more eyes for critique on research improves development of knowledge
<br>Increased visibility, retrievability, and dataset citations aid in career building
<br>R Markdown, Jupyter notebooks and Anaconda Virtual environments allow for simplified computational reproduction of research
<br><br>
<br>Statistical power: the probability to reject the null hypothesis when it is in fact false (~80% for funding agencies)
<br>Sample size calculations estimates sample size based on desired width of a confidence interval for the targeted effect and reduce the risk of running low-powered studies
<br><br>
<br>Be familiar with the correct interpretations and misinterpretations of p-values, confidence intervals, and statistical power
<br>Data processing, cleaning, transformation, handling missing data, and statistical inference precede p-values and confidence interval calculations
<br><br><br>
<br>
<br><br>
<br>
]]></description><link>digital-garden\ten-simple-rules-in-good-research-practice.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Digital Garden/Ten Simple Rules in Good Research Practice.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:33:04 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>